<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Universal love being an epistle given forth by the Spirit of God / through his suffering servant, Will. Gibson ; and is to be sent into all nations and countries where the Lord God hath rais'd a people to worship him in spirit and in truth ; to be read in his pure fear in their publick assemblies and private families for their edification and comfort.</title>
            <author>Gibson, William, 1629-1684.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1671</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 44 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 12 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A42717</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing G688</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R38757</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">18110520</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 18110520</idno>
            <idno type="VID">106804</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A42717)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 106804)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1124:8)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Universal love being an epistle given forth by the Spirit of God / through his suffering servant, Will. Gibson ; and is to be sent into all nations and countries where the Lord God hath rais'd a people to worship him in spirit and in truth ; to be read in his pure fear in their publick assemblies and private families for their edification and comfort.</title>
                  <author>Gibson, William, 1629-1684.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>22 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London?] printed :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1679.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Society of Friends --  Pastoral letters and charges.</term>
               <term>Society of Friends --  Doctrines.</term>
               <term>Holy Spirit.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:106804:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Univerſal Love.</p>
            <p>Being an EPISTLE Given forth by the Spirit of God, Through his Suffering Servant <hi>Will. Gibſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>AND Is to be ſent into all Nations and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, where the Lord God hath rais'd a People to worſhip him in Spirit and in Truth; to be read in his Pure Fear, in their publick Aſſemblies and private Families, for their Edification and Comfort.</p>
            <p>Printed in the Year, 1671.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:106804:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:106804:2"/>
            <head>Univerſal Love, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>ALL Friends every where, who have believ'd in Chriſt Jeſus, the true Light, which lighteth every man that cometh into the World, that all men in him might be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve and be ſav'd: Whoſe Underſtandings he hath open'd by his Spiritual Light, ſhining in your hearts; and thereby hath given you to know your Duty towards God, and Man; and thereby hath drawn you to confeſs him before men, and to make publique Confeſſion and Profeſſion of the Worſhip of God, which is in Spirit and in Truth. All in the ſame Pure Spiritual Light, ſtedfaſtly continue, Waiting, Walking, and Abiding; that ſo every one of you may receive Strength from the Lord God of Heaven and Earth, to perform your Duty unto him in all things; yea, to ſerve him with your whole ſtrength, as he hath commanded; and to do that which is Juſt, Righteous, and Equal unto all People, with whom you have to do: That ſo you may ſhine as Lights in the World; and that your Light may ſo ſhine before men, that they may ſee your good works, and Glorifie your Father, which is in Heaven: Chriſt the true Light ſaith, <hi>No man lights a Candle, &amp; putteth it under a Beſhel,</hi> (that is, he doth not hide or cover the Light) <hi>but ſetteth it on a Candle-ſtick, that it may give light unto all that are in the Houſe.</hi> So ſee that your Light be not hid, vail'd, nor cover'd; but that it may ſhine forth in its Splender and Brightneſs, leading and gui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding you into all Truth, according to his Promiſe, who ſaid, <hi>I will ſend you the Spirit of Truth, and he ſhall lead you into all Truth:</hi> And this the Lord God hath fulfill'd unto a little Remnant, and is fulfilling it daily, and will fulfil it unto many Thouſands, who yet <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>it in Darkneſs, under the region and ſhaddow of Death: Glory to his Bleſſed Name for his tender Mercy, which
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:106804:3"/>he hath mightily ſhed abroad in this our Age, in and through the Light Chriſt Jeſus, who is the Way to God the Father; who is made manifeſt in us, to take away and deſtroy all Sin, becauſe it is of the Devil, and is againſt God, and Grieves and Diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours him; therefore will God have it taken away and deſtroy'd by Jeſus Chriſt his divine Wiſdom and Power; that ſo Man and Woman may be wholly freed from that Corruptible Bondage, which the Devil hath brought them into, by leading them into Sin, which hath ſeperated them from him, and with-holden his Bleſſings from them; that ſo again they may be a Free People, as it was in the beginning, before Tranſgreſſion was: And this is the Glorious Liberty of the Sons and Daughters of God, which Chriſt did reſtore many into in the Apoſtles dayes, which Work he is now Gloriouſly carrying on in theſe our dayes; Glory, yea, Glory be unto the Lord our God forever, for the ſame. For, now the Children of the Lord, are taught by him; and his Sons and Daughters are led by his Spirit into all Truth; and the Peace of all ſuch is plentiful as a River, whoſe Streams never fail; and ſuch can ſenſibly ſay, Good is the Lord, and worthy is he to be Feared, Loved, and Served for ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more.</p>
            <p>So all Friends, who have taken a Profeſſion of the Holy Name of the Lord God upon you, walk worthy of that Holy Call, wherewith the Lord, in his tender Mercy, hath called you. And in all your Buying, and Selling, and Exchanging of God's good Creatures, in Markets, and Fairs, and in all other places, abide in the Pure Spirit of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, that therein you may be a ſweet Savour of God unto his own Witneſs in the hearts of all People that ſee you and hear you; all keeping in the Doctrine of Chriſt, who ſaid, <hi>Let your yea be yea, and your nay nay, in your Communication; and what is more cometh of Evil:</hi> So all keep in ſound Speech, which the Spirit of Truth doth lead into; that ſo you may all Glorifie God in buying, and ſelling, and exchanging of his good Creatures, that ſo he may Bleſs you in the uſe of them; for, his Bleſſing is, and will be, upon the Faithful. So, let all words be ſpoken in the Pure <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ear and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel of the Lord in buying and ſelling, and exchanging, and
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:106804:3"/>in all your Handicraft Trades, and Labours; and keep out of that which is ſuperfluous and needleſs; and ſo your Words and Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons will be Few, Sound, and Savory, without any Deceit; and this will miniſter Grace unto the Hearers: And Bleſſed are all thoſe that ſo do; their Subſtance is, and will be Bleſſed.</p>
            <p>And all Friends, that Travel up and down in the World, about your Occaſions, and come to lie, or be at Inns, Victu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alling-houſes, or Taverns, where Beat, Wine, Ale, or other ſtrong Liquors are ſold; keep in the Pure Spirit of the Lord God, that thereby you may be preſerved Pure and clean unto God, in the uſe of eating and drinking of God's good Creatures; that ſo, whether you Eat or Drink, or whatſoever you do, you may do it in the Pure Wiſdom of the Lord God, to his Glory; And not to drink in exceſs, to ſpend God's good Creatures upon unclean Luſts; but to be true Witneſſes for God againſt all ſuch things, where ever you <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> that ſo God's Bleſſing you may all feel in your Buſineſs. <hi>Be not Drunk with Wine,</hi> ſaid the Apoſtle, <hi>but be ſia'd with the Spirit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And all Friends, in your particular <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, in your daily Labour and Buſineſs, all watch in the H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>pirit of God, that the Enemy of your Soul may not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> your Minds into Lightneſs, Vain-words, nor Laughte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, nor Idle-jeſting, nor Anger, Wrath, Strife, nor Buſineſs one againſt another; but that you may live in unfeigned L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ve together, and ſerving one an other in the ſame; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> being ſubject unto their own Maſters, ſerving <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> with Eye-ſervice, but with an Up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right Heart, as unto Gods For, whatſoever <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> any man doth, he ſhall receive a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>rd, whether he be Bond or Free: And Maſters giving unto their Servants that which is right in the ſight of God; and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, as they would be done unto: And Children obeying their Parents in the Lord, which is juſt and right in the ſight or the Lord. The Eye of the Lord is over the Righteous, and his Ear i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> open unto their Cries; but the Face of the Lord is againſt every one, that doth Evil.</p>
            <p>And all Friends, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Parents of Children, walk ye be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> Wiſdom of the Lord God, and be good Examples unto them in all things; directing their Minds unto
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:106804:4"/>the Principle of God, when they are capable to receive Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection: And let not your Fleſhly Affections be drawn out, by the Enemy of your immortal ſouls, to encourage your Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren in Wildneſs, nor any Unrighteous Word or Action; but ſtill, in the Wiſdom of the Lord God, watch over them, and ſhew your Diſlike unto the Evil in your Children; and ſeaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly (in the Wiſdom of the Lord) Reproving and Correcting them for the Evil, and Admoniſhing them to that which is Good; not in Raſhneſs, nor Fretting; but in that weighty Spirit of the Lord God, which will keep your own minds Cool and Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate; and that will not harden your Children's Hearts, nor provoke them to Wrath againſt you.</p>
            <p>And Friends, Strive not ſo much to get great Riches in this World, for your Children, as to bring them up in the Fear of the Lord God; for, if they come into the Fear of the Lord God, and Serve him, though you have little to leave them, yet will the Lord God provide for them; and if they do not Love, Fear, and Serve God, much outward Riches will do them no good; but they will be hurt by it, as we may ſee many are at this day, who had outward Riches left them by their Parents; who were not train'd up by their Parents in the pure Fear of the Lord God; but contrariwiſe, in Pride, Sports, Plays, Games, Vain words, Lightneſs, Wildneſs, Swearing, Lying, and Drunkenneſs, &amp;c. and ſo, growing up in Wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, which took root in them in their Youth: They ſpend their outward Riches, left unto them by their Parents, upon their Ungodly Luſts, and ſo Grieve and Diſhonour the Lord the more thereby; and ſo, it had been better for them, that they had ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver had it.</p>
            <p>And all Friends every where, Keep in the Pure Spirit of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, which will keep you all Meek, and truly Lowly and Humble in Heart and Mind; that your Adorning may not be that, of putting on of Rich or Coſtly Apparel; but that it may be the hidden Man of the Heart, in that which is not corruptible; even the Ornament of a Meek, Pure, and Quiet Spirit, which with the Lord God is of great Price,</p>
            <p>And be you not, nor your Children, Conformable unto this World, and its Faſhions, and Cuſtoms, and Manners, which
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:106804:4"/>are Corrupt, and Vain, and Changeable, and aboundantly Sinful, in Riotouſneſs, Gluttonny, Drunkenneſs, and Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfluity of Apparel; while they ſuffer the Poor to lie languiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the Streets, for want of a Supply of thoſe things which are needful: And this is a crying Abomination in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and many other Parts of that, call'd <hi>Chriſtendom,</hi> which is a great Shame to the Biſhops, who are call'd, <hi>Reverend Fathers in God;</hi> a Name very unfit for their Unmerciful, Ungod-like, and Unchriſt-like Nature: For, God is Love, and thoſe that dwell in him, they dwell in Love; and Love doth feed the Hungry, and clothe the Naked with a Garment. So the Biſhops, Prieſts, and Rulers, and Rich, and Fat, and Wanton People, who ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer their Poor Neighbours, yea, and their own Church-Members, to ſuffer want of Food and Raiment, (while they are Eating, and Drinking, and clothing, in exceſs, without the Fear of God) have not a Habitation in God, who is Love, nor in Chriſt Jeſus. So be not you like unto them, but keep in the Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of the Lord, in putting on your Apparel, and in all things elſe, that you may preach forth Righteouſneſs in the whole courſe of your Life, and manner of your Converſation.</p>
            <p>And all dear Friends every where, who have been call'd by the Lord God out of the worſhips of the World, which are vain, into his own pure Worſhip, which is in Spirit and Truth; continue ſtedfaſt with the Lord in all things, I tenderly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech you (as mov'd by him)</p>
            <p>Oh Friends! You that have been moved and commanded by the Lord God of Heaven and Earth, to with-draw your ſelves from the falſe Teachers, who are ſet up by men, and not by the Lord God; whoſe Work hath been, and yet is, to preach up War, Strife, and Perſecution, and to ſet People one againſt another, to deſtroy one another. O keep your Teſtimony pure unto the End, that ſo you may all receive a <hi>full Reward</hi> of the Lord God.</p>
            <p>O Friends, you know what War the Prieſts have prepar'd againſt us, ſince the time the Lord, in his tender Mercy, let us ſee their Deceit, and call'd us out from among'ſt them, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrain'd us, to forbear putting into their Mouthes: What Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vock
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:106804:5"/>and Spoil have they made of our Goods, and impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of our Bodies (divers until Death?) But O how hath the Lord born up a Remnant (who loves him and fears him) as up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Eagles Wings! And hath made us to bear joyfully the ſpoiling of our Goods, and the impriſonment of our Bodies; <hi>Glory,</hi> yea, <hi>Glory unto his Holy Bleſſed Vame forever.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So all be <hi>valiant</hi> for the Lord God, and his Worſhip, which he hath call'd us into; and have an Eye unto the Recompence of Reward, which the Lord God hath in ſtore for thoſe who continue in Well-doing unto the End. So the Lord God Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty ſtrengthen you all with his Mighty Power, in your in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Man; and let not an <hi>Evil Mind</hi> of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nbelief</hi> ſpring up in any, to diſtruſt the Lord concerning outward things: For, he who feeds the <hi>Ravens,</hi> and clothes the <hi>Graſs,</hi> and takes Care for <hi>Sparrows,</hi> he hath provided for us, and doth and will pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide for us, if we do abide in Faithfulneſs unto him, he will not ſuffer us to want that which is good for us, that <hi>all the Faithful are fully ſatisfied in:</hi> And many have deep Experience of his Fatherly Care over them, which hath begotten a depth of Love in their hearts unto him; by which they are made ſtrong in the Faith, to <hi>follow</hi> him through the greateſt Hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips: And ſo we know him a God near at hand, Mighty to Save; and do endure Afflictions with Chearfulneſs, becauſe we do inherit his Mighty Power, by which we are made Conquerers over <hi>Hell,</hi> and <hi>Death,</hi> and all the Rage and Fury of Man.</p>
            <p>And all dear Friends in <hi>England,</hi> and elſe-where, who have been, and yet are under great Sufferings, in the Spoil of your Goods, and Impriſonment of your Bodies, for your Pure Obedience to the Living God, in meeting together to Worſhip him in Spirit and Truth: Happy are you, and great is, and will be your Reward, if you continue in <hi>Well-doing</hi> unto the End.</p>
            <p>O Friends! Rejoyce in the Lord, who hath given you Abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity to ſuffer for his Glorious Name's ſake; knowing, that it is not only given unto us, to believe in Chriſt Jeſus, but alſo to
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:106804:5"/>ſuffer with him, and for his ſake; and if we do ſuffer with him, we ſhall alſo Raign with him: But if any ſhould refuſe to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer with him, they cannot Raign with him; <hi>For</hi> (ſaid Chriſt) <hi>he that denies me before men, him will I deny before my Father, which is in Heaven:</hi> And he ſaid, <hi>Whoſoever doth forſake Father or Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, Wife or Children, Lands or Living, for my Name's ſake; he ſhall receive in this World Many-fold, and in the World to come, Everlaſting Life:</hi> And this is a faithful Saying, and worthy to be believ'd and accepted by all; and it is believ'd by Thouſands, and the Truth of it ſeen and witneſs'd inwardly; Glory to the Lord God for the ſame.</p>
            <p>O the Glorious Powerful Preſence of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, which Thouſands do enjoy in their Hearts and Souls! Which doth give them perfect dominion over Sin, and the Devil, who is the Author of it. O my dear Friends! This is a Many-fold Reward for our Sufferings; and I do ſenſibly ſay, and affirm on God's Behalf, That the Sufferings, which do attend us in this World, for the Truth's ſake, are not worthy to be compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to the Glorious Power of the Lord, which is already re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veal'd in us, who have ſteadfaſtly believ'd in him, and freely have been given up to ſuffer with him, and for him: For, as our Tribulations have been increas'd, for his ſake; our Conſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in him hath much more abounded; ſo that we can truly and ſenſibly ſay, as thoſe, who ſuffer'd with him before us, did ſay, <hi>Greater is he that is in us, then he that is in the World;</hi> by whom we do overcome the World, and the Devil, who is the godd of it: And he hath made us Conquerors through his Love, Life, and Power; and ſo we can bring in our Teſtimony for him, to his Glory, and our own everlaſting Comfort, <hi>That he is able to ſave un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the utmost all that come to the Father by him.</hi> So dear Friends every where, be <hi>Valiant</hi> and <hi>Chearful</hi> in your Sufferings for the Pretious Living Truth, and Way of the Living God, in which you are come to know your ſouls Salvation; and as good Souldiers of Chriſt Jeſus, endure Afflictions, and rejoyce in them, and through them, and over them; and Raign in the Lamb's Patience, over all Perſecution and Perſecutors, unto the End of your Dayes, in this World: For, dear Friends, It is thoſe that endure unto the End, that muſt inherit Everlaſting Life,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:106804:6"/>and the Heavenly Joy and Divine Riches, which is beyond what can be declar'd in words: <hi>But if any man draws back, my Soul ſhall have no pleaſure in him,</hi> ſaith the Lord God: So all Friends, prize your precious Time, and preſs forward in the Truth, that ſo you may grow more and more Spiritually-minded, our of Earthly-mindedneſs; for, we brought nothing into this World. and it is certain, we can take nothing out: ſo having Food and Raiment, let us therewith be content; for, here we have no continuing City; but though our Earthly Houſe of this Tabernacle were diſſolv'd, yet have we an Inward Eternal Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitation in the Lord; and though our outward Man periſh, yet do we know a renewing of ſtrength in the inward Man, day by day: And our light Affliction, which is but as for a Moment, worketh unto us a far more and exceeding weight of Glory, while we look not at the loſs of <hi>Temperal, Outward,</hi> and <hi>Periſhing Riches;</hi> but at the gain of Spiritual and Eternal Riches, which the Lord our God is aboundantly inriching us withal, in this the Day of the Manifeſtation of his Great and Glorious Power and Wiſdom in us. So dear Friends, we have no cauſe to be dicourag'd; for we certainly know, That the Lord God is with us, and he will plead our Cauſe with all our Adverſaries; and he is ſtronger then them all; and by his Strength we are upheld, and made bold as Lions, to meet together to Worſhip him, as he hath commanded us: And all our Enemies are not able to pluck us out of our Heavenly Father's Hand; but as Chriſt hath ſaid, we do witneſs it to be true, who ſaid, <hi>My Father is greater then all; and no man is able to pluck my Sheep out of my Father's Hand.</hi> So, God Almighty <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> you all my dear Friends, and Heavenly Relations, and Spiritual Kindred, whom the Living God hath Redeem'd out of the World, which lieth in Wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs, by his Almighty Power, which hath wrought <hi>Mightily</hi> and <hi>Effectually</hi> in you, for your Redemption out of ſin; and hath brought a Remnant to ſit together in Heavenly Places in Chriſt Jeſus, where the Devil and Sin hath no place: And he is daily increaſing the ſtrength of the leaſt of his People, who wait upon him in the Meaſure of his pure Light, Grace, and Spirit, already made manifeſt; and thoſe that are Faithful in a little, he doth make to inherit great Riches; he bears his
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:106804:6"/>Lambs in his Arms, and gently leads on thoſe who are wait<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon him in the Way of his Righteous Judgments; and thoſe that do own him in the Way of his Righteous Judgments, he doth ſhew Mercy unto: and though they do know a time, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in they do ſow in Tears; yet they do not long abide in that E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate (but he brings them to reap in Joy) as it is witneſſed at this day by Thouſands, who have known a time, wherein the Hand of the Lord hath been heavy upon them, becauſe of Sin; but he hath blotted out and forgiven thoſe that have been brought unto true Repentance, and a Forſaking of Sin, by his Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Judgments: and ſo, Times of Refreſhment are come unto thoſe who have patiently born his Righteous Judgments; and now ſuch can ſing forth the high Praiſes of the Lord, in the Land of the Living, in the Beauty of Holineſs. O the Beauty, the Beauty that is in Holineſs! <hi>And without Holineſs none can be accepted of the Lord God,</hi> who is Holy; <hi>for Holineſs becomes his Houſe and People forever:</hi> And the Temple of God is Holy, which Temple Faithful Suffering Friends are, who have own'd him in the Way of his Righteous Judgments, and have been cleans'd thereby; in whom he hath appear'd as a Refiner, with Fire; and as a Fuller, with Soap. O Friends, How precious is that Freedom and Liberty, which Chriſt Jeſus, the Power and Wiſdom of God, hath wrought in us and for us? O ſtand all in it forever; and none ſuffer your ſelves to be again entangled with the Yoak of Bondage, which the Enemy of your Immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Souls once had you under: O remember thoſe bitter Dayes and Hours, which we ſpent in Darkneſs, when we knew not the Way of Life and Peace! O remember how we did wander as Blind Men, and could find no Comfort in all the Earth unto our Immortal Souls; and then the Lord God of tender Mercy, heard our Cries and Groans in ſecret, and hath rewarded us Richly! O let his tender Mercy be had in Everlaſting Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance by all that have partaken of the ſame!</p>
            <p>And all Friends, Keep your firſt Love unto the Lord, and his pure Living Way, which he hath brought you into; and none look back into the World, and its glory, which will Periſh and come to an End: But keep your Minds chaſt unto the Living
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:106804:7"/>God, who hath ſhew'd you ſuch great Kindneſs: O let not the Cares of this World, and the Deceitfulneſs of Riches, and the Love of other things choak nor hinder the growth of the pure Seed of Life in any of you! nor let not the Storm or Heat of Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution drive any of you away from the Lord God; but all keep your Virginity unto the End.</p>
            <p>And all Friends every where, Keep your Meetings in the Name of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, who never <hi>fell</hi> nor <hi>chang'd;</hi> and feel his Living Vertue in the mid'ſt of you, keeping you Quick, Freſh, and Lively; out of all Careleſneſs, Dulneſs, and Drou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs; for, theſe are Uncomly. So all have a great Care to keep out of ſuch things; and all wait upon the Lord in the Comly Order, that you may all be Refreſh'd by him, in your Meetings; and that you may all have Cauſe to ſay, <hi>Good is the Lord, and worthy is he to be waited upon; for he feeds the Hungry with Good Things:</hi> And as all do diligently wait upon God in the Meaſure of his Holy Spirit, which he hath given unto them to profit withal, they will feel a true Hungering and Thirſting after the Righteouſneſs of God, to be made Partakers of it more and more; and unto ſuch the Bleſſing doth belong; and God will deal bountifully with ſuch; for he delighteth in his People's Diligence: And as it is written, <hi>The Diligent Hand maketh Rich; but the Sluggard ſhall be clothed with Ruggs, whoſe Field grows over with Briars and Thorns:</hi> And Man, in ſuch a State is Miſerable, and ſhall not be Crown'd with Honour, which God gives unto the Faithful; nor can he in that State dye in Peace with the Lord. Therefore all be Faithfal unto the Lord God in all things, that when your dayes are ended in this World, you may reſt Eternally in the Boſom of the Lord; as it is written, <hi>Bleſſed are the Dead which die in the Lord; for they ſhall rest from their Labour, and their Works ſhall follow them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And Friends, Our God (who is the True and Living God) he is Love, as it is written of him; and all People, who do dwell in God; they do dwell in unfeigned Love one unto an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other, and alſo unto their Enemies, as the Lord Jeſus hath commanded: In which Love of God we are raiſed up to Worſhip him, and in it to watch one over another, and to
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:106804:7"/>build up one another in Holineſs; and in it are we Comforted and Edified, and are made of one Heart and Mind, and made near and dear one unto another, and truly tender one over an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other, and careful one of anothers Good every way; and in true Humility to Honour and Eſteem one another, and thereby led to be juſt and true in all our Words and Actions, one to, and concerning another, and to and concerning all our Enemies, in which we do ſeek the Eternal Good of all People; and in which we do live in ſweet Unity, and pure Peace together, as doth become the Family of God.</p>
            <p>O how ſweet is the Unity in God's Spirit of Love and Life, in which the Bond of Peace is kept, without BREACH! For, in the Spirit of Love and Life, all Friends being kept (which keeps all Upright, Juſt, and Pure) the Bond of Peace cannot be broken.</p>
            <p>So in this, the Lord God of Heaven and Earth preſerve you all, my dear Friends, (unto whom my Love is dear and near in the Lord) that ſo all your hearts may be full of the Pure Love of God, which thinketh nor doth no evil unto any (but doth good unto all) that you may be known to be the Diſciples of Chriſt, who ſaid, <hi>Every Tree ſhall be known by its Fruit;</hi> and ſaid, <hi>A Good Tree cannot bring forth Evil Fruit;</hi> and he ſaid, <hi>The Good Man, our of the Good Treaſury of his Heart, bringeth forth Good Things,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But he ſaid, <hi>The Evil Man, out of the Evil Treaſury of his Heart, bringeth forth Evil Things:</hi> Which are the Fruits of the Fleſh, begotten therein by the power of Darkneſs, which doth Rule in the Hearts of all the Wicked and Ungodly, upon the Face of the whole Earth.</p>
            <p>Which Evil Things are, Envy, Malice, Murder, Oppreſſion, Injuſtice, Falſe-judgment, Idolatry, Strife, Hypocriſie, Defrau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding one another in Words and Actions, Evil Imaginations, and Evil Thoughts, and Evil Words, Pride, Covetouſneſs, Swearing, Lying, Drunkenneſs, Whoredom, Thieft, Light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, Wildneſs, Vain-Laughter, Idle-Jeſting, Whiſpering. Falſe-accuſing, and Tale-bearing to ſow Strife, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>So all Friends, who do make Profeſſion of the pure Truth, and perfect Way of the Lord, and to be Followers of the Lord
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:106804:8"/>Jeſus Chriſt, the Patient and Innocent Lamb of God, who did not Sin, neither was Deceit at any time (in any thing) found in his Mouth; See how you do follow him, your Living Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; and perfect Pattern, I ſay, Search all with the Heart, ſearching Spirit of the Lord God; and ſee that you ſtand out of all thoſe, before mention'd Evils, &amp;c. For, becauſe of them comes the Wrath of God upon thoſe who do continue in them, and do not believe in Chriſt, and follow him, who leads out of them, and deſtroyes them: <hi>For, no <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nclean Thing can inherit God's Kingdom.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But Glory to the Lord God, He hath Redeem'd a Remnant from ſuch of the before mention'd Evils, as they were guilty of who now know a Pure Peaceable Reſt, and a quiet Habitation in him, in whom he workes to Will and to Do of his own Good Pleaſure; and he is daily Redeeming thoſe that wait upon him in the Wayes of his Righteous Judgments.</p>
            <p>And ſo all who do profeſs the Truth, and live and walk con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to it, and thereby cauſe the Way of Truth to be Evil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpoken of, and harden the Hearts of Unbelievers againſt it, and ſo ſhut the Kingdom of Heaven againſt men, not entring themſelves, but by their Evil Example hinder others: If they do not Repent while they have time, and amend their wayes, and walk orderly, as becomes the Goſpel; heavy will the Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of God fall upon them in the End.</p>
            <p>And all ſuch who have once known and Profeſſed the Way of Truth, and in ſome Meaſure (and for ſome time) have walked in it; but now are turn'd away from it, into the Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godlineſs again, like the Dog to his Vomit, and the Sow that was waſh'd, to the wallowing in the Mire; and now are grown ſo hard-hearted, that they can ſpeak Evil of the Way of Truth, and oppoſe it; and hate, contemn, ſcorn, and reproach thoſe who live in it, and ſuffer for it: (My Soul pitties them) Miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable is their Condition. O that it were in their Heart to ſeek a Place of Repentance! then it may be, the Lord might ſhew Mercy unto them: But if they do go on in Gainſaying (as <hi>Core</hi> did) then had it been better for them, that they had never been born; for, Everlaſting Torment and Anguiſh will be the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward of their wicked work.</p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:106804:8"/>
            <p>And dear Friends, and Brethren, and Siſters every where, This Teſtimony am I mov'd of the Lord God to bear for your Conſolation, <hi>(viz.)</hi> That this is the True and Living Faith, wherein we ſtand, who have believ'd in the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, the true Light, and have follow'd the Leadings of his Bleſſed Holy Spirit, which hath led us out of the Evil that is in the World, by which we have been crucified unto the World, and its Glory, and the many Sinful Cuſtoms and Faſhions, that are of it, and in it; and by which we have been led into a Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Innocent Converſation: And by, and in this Faith, we do live to God; and in it are we brought to Love God (Uprightly) and to ſerve him with our whole ſtrength: For, this Faith is his own Gift, which hath wrought by Love, in us, Effectual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, to the purifying of our Hearts and Spirits, which were defill'd with ſin: And in this Holy Faith is our Religion and Worſhip Pure, and is of the Pure God, and ſo is accepted by him; and we have the Witneſs of this in our own Hearts: And we do certainly know, that we are of God, by his Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, which he hath given us: And this is the one ſtanding Faith, which is God's Gift, in which the Pure, Standing, Unchangeable Worſhip of God is again renew'd, and ſet up among'ſt us, as it was in the Apoſtles dayes; Glory, yea, Glory be to the Lord God forever, whoſe day of Light and Life is now (again) made manifeſt in, and unto us, as it was in the Apoſtles dayes; and it ſhines Gloriouſly among'ſt us to our great Conſolation.</p>
            <p>O the Glory, the Glory of the Lord God! O how doth it ſhine in the Aſſemblies of the Righteous! Overcoming, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhing, and Melting the Hearts of the Upright, and making them more glad, then they that have great increaſe of Corn, and Wine, and Oyle. And we can truly ſay, The Lord hath dealt bountifully with us; our Lot is fallen in a Fruitful Hill, and we have a goodly Inheritance; and this is our Inheritance, The everlaſting Power and Wiſdom of the Lord our God, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by we are redeem'd out of the Evil that is in the World, and through Faith in the ſame, are upheld in Purity, wherein
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:106804:9"/>our Peace and Joy is great at this day, and no man can take it from us.</p>
            <p>And my dear Friends, I know the Lord God is daily en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſing your Faith, who have been freely given up to ſuffer for Righteouſneſs ſake; ſo that you can ſay (with the Prophet) <hi>Though there be no Flocks in the Fold, and though the Fruits of the Earth be taken from you, for your pure Obedience unto God; yet can you not Murmur at it, but do ſtill Rejoyce in the Lord God of your Salvation;</hi> and can caſt your Care upon him, knowing he doth care for you, as a Tender Father, for his Tender and Obedient Children.</p>
            <p>And my dear Friends, Though all the falſe Worſhippers and Apoſtates upon the whole Earth, ſhould joyn together, and ſeek to deſtroy our Teſtimony, and pure Faith, and pure Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip; yet can they never do it: But the Teſtimony, and Faith, and Worſhip, into which we are gather'd by the Lord our God, it ſhall ſtand and remain, when all their Fighting, Perſecuting, and Blood-thirſty Faiths, and Religions, and Worſhips, and Falſe Teſtimonies are gone, and ended.</p>
            <p>And we ſhall yet live to Praiſe the Lord our God, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding all the Rage and Fury of our Enemies. And though Sufferings may attend us for a little time, yet will they be ended in the Lord's Time; and he doth ſuffer us to be try'd, but it is not in Enmity to us, but in Love, that we may be gather'd unto him, out of all things which periſh with the uſing; and that we may know him to be our Strength; and that he may ſhew forth his Vertue and Power in us, in our Sufferings; and that People, who ſit in Darkneſs, and whoſe Hearts are ſet on Earthly Things, may ſee, that he hath redeem'd a People from the Earth, who can ſuffer the Loſs of all earthly Enjoyments, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then to deny their Teſtimony Faith and Religion, which he hath call'd them into: And by Friends Faithfulneſs herein, is the Lord God Glorified, and the Underſtandings of People opened; and they come to ſee the difference betwixt thoſe, who do profeſs Chriſt in words, and Faithful Friends, who do enjoy him in
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:106804:9"/>Life and Power: And ſo, the Wiſe Man's Houſe upon the Rock comes to be known from the Fool's Houſe upon the Sand; that ſo thoſe, who are diſſatisfied with the Dead, Huskey, Falſe Worſhips that are in the World, may know where to centre and ſit down, even with us, who are become the Flock and He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritage of the Lord God.</p>
            <p>And God's Worſhip in the Spirit and in the Truth, which he hath ſet up among'ſt us, and into which we are gather'd, it muſt ſpread over the Nations and Kingdoms of the World; and the Nations and Kingdoms of this World muſt become our God's, and his Chriſt's (as it is written) This hath the Lord God Decreed, and all his Enemies cannot reverſe nor alter this his Decree.</p>
            <p>And God will certainly throw down all the Fighting, Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuting, Blood-thirſty Faiths, and Worſhips, and Religions upon the Face of the Earth, which have been ſet up in the Fallen, Earthly, and Senſual, and Diviliſh-wiſdom of Wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Men; about which they have ſhed the Blood of many Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent People, who have been taught of God, and therefore could not bow unto their Deviliſh Inventions.</p>
            <p>And the Living, Powerful, Almighty, Dreadful God, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore whom all the ſtrength of his Enemies is but as a Thred of Tow in the bot fiery Flame, he is riſen to execute his Judgments upon the Old Red Draggon, the Devil, who hath made the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, like the Raging Sea, throwing forth Mire and Dirt, and hath ſet People to devour one another about Religion, Faith, and Worſhip, like Wolves, Lions, and Dogs: And the Lord God will certainly Plague him, and Bind him; and REDEEM the Nations from under his Accurſed power.</p>
            <p>And the Great Whore, who hath been drunk with the Blood of the Saints, who have kept the Teſtimony of Jeſus (which is the Spirit of Propheſie) Her will God judge, and the Beaſt, and Falſe Prophets, and all whoſe Hands and Hearts are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filed with ſhedding Innocent Blood; the Wrath &amp; Indignation of the Lord God will be heavy upon them: And God will certainly Waſte, Conſume, and Confound, with his Righteous Judgments, the Stock and Root of the Wicked and Ungodly, and will Rout
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:106804:10"/>Wickedneſs and Ungodlineſs out of the Nations of the Earth; and will plant the Nations with Righteouſneſs, Holineſs, and Purity, that ſo he may be Exalted over all the Works of his Hands.</p>
            <p>And the Lamb Chriſt Jeſus, the Prince of Life and Peace, who comes not to deſtroy mens Lives, but to ſave them, He muſt have the Victory over the Dragon, Beaſt, Whore, and Falſe Prophets, whoſe Work hath been, and ſtill is, to deſtroy both the Souls and Bodies of People.</p>
            <p>And all Nations that come to be ſav'd, muſt walk in the Light of the Lamb Chriſt Jeſus, in which Light we do now Raign with him, over all Deceit, and over all the falſe Worſhips in the World, (notwithſtanding our outward Sufferings) for our Raign is Spiritual and Inward.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <p>AND all Friends, who are newly convinced, or ſuch who may be Young and Weak in the Faith; God hath put ſomething into my Heart to write unto you, for your Eſtabliſhment in the perfect Way of the Lord.</p>
               <p>And this is God's Counſel unto you all, Let your Faith remain firm and ſtedfaſt in Chriſt Jeſus, the true Light and Life of men; and all wait upon God in that Meaſure of his Bleſſed Light and Spirit, which he in his tender Mercy hath given unto you, to profit withal; that therein you may all grow into a living Sence and Knowledge of God (which hath been loſt by Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion) that you may all come to be renew'd up into the Pure, Spiritual, Heavenly, and Divine Image of God, in which man was made in the Beginning <hi>(A Noble Vine; wholy of a Right Seed)</hi> So, all wait to know your Birth of the Immortal Incorruptible Seed (which is the Word) of God, which Lives and Abides forever; which Word, Seed, Light, and Life is to be found, receiv'd, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy'd
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:106804:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>within People: And Bleſſed are they who do be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve in it, and continue ſtedfaſt unto the End; in them it doth take root, and bring forth Fruit aboundantly unto the Praiſe and Glory of God, and unto their aboundant Joy and endleſs Comfort: So all you, that have been bound down in ſin, by the great Enemy of your immortal Souls, and who have known great Diſtreſſes, Anguiſh, and Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row becauſe thereof; Wait you all diligently upon God in the Light, which doth ſhew unto you your preſent con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, and therein you will receive Power from God, who is Light, over Sin and the Devil, who is the Author of it; and ſo will come to feel and know Chriſt (the true Seed) in you, to bruiſe the Old <hi>Serpent</hi>'s Head, yea, his whole ſtrength and power in you to waſte and deſtroy, and he will bring you out of the Bondage of Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption into the Glorious Liberty of the Sons and Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of God; and ſo you will come to know, that <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Christ</hi> is greater in you, then the <hi>Wicked-ſpirit</hi> (call'd the <hi>Devil</hi>) who will certainly bind him, and caſt him out, and take from him all his Armor, wherein he truſted.</p>
               <p>But for the Accompliſhment of theſe great and weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Matters, <hi>You must all wait upon God with much Diligence and Patience; and let the Pure Judgments of God freely take hold of all that is Unrighteous, and contrary to God in you; that ſo the Pure, Powerful, Quickning Word of Eternal Life may freely operate and work mightily in you, as a Fire, Hammer, and Sword; that ſo by it you may be perfectly ſet free.</hi> For, there is not any thing elſe, that can make free from ſin. And this is an E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Record, and True Living Teſtimony, which the Eternal and Engrafted Word of Life <hi>(which doth Reign in my Heart, and in the Hearts of my Faithful Friends)</hi> doth bear unto you, and unto all People upon the face of the whole Earth.</p>
               <p>And whoſoever doth Write, Print, or Speak againſt
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:106804:11"/>the Word, Spirit, Light, and Life of God and Chriſt within Man and Woman; and do ſay, <hi>That it is not able to deſtroy all ſin, nor able to lead into all Truth, nor able to up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold Man and Woman in it</hi> They are all Lyars, Deceivers, and Falſe-witneſſes; and their Words, Writings, and Teſtimonies herein are not of God, nor for him; but are abſolutely of the Devil, and for him, whoſe Kingdom ſtands in Sin (which Chriſt is come to throw down, and wholy to deſtroy: So let none believe them in thoſe things; for, if they do, they will be undone by it.</p>
               <p>And ſo, all keep out of all the Shadows and Figures, which do not make the Heart and Conſcience perfect in the Sight of God.</p>
               <p>And all keep to Chriſt, the Immortal and Eternal Husband, and know him to Baptize you with his Spirit and Life, which doth burn up the Corruptions: And this is the one ſtanding Baptiſm, of which the Apoſtle did te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie; and the one Faith, of which he did teſtifie is, to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve in Chriſt the Light, and Life, and Word, and Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of God, who ſaid, <hi>There is one Lord, one Faith, one Baptiſm, one God over all, through all, and in you all:</hi> So, who are come to witneſs this, have no need of outward Shaddows and Elements (which are but beggarly in compariſon of the <hi>Life</hi> and <hi>Subſtance</hi>) So, in Chriſt, the Subſtance, Life, and Light, all are to come to ſit down in the Heavenly Places, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Fleſh and Blood, which comes down from Heaven (&amp; feeding upon it, which gives Life, and this is the Lord's Supper) with which he feeds his Faithful Followers, by which they are made ſtrong to reſiſt the Devil, and to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come him: So, in and with this the Lord God preſerve you all, and by it ſtrengthen you in your Inward Man, that you may follow the Lord God with <hi>Chearfulneſs,</hi> that you may walk in the Way of the Lord <hi>valiantly,</hi> and never be
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:106804:11"/>weary of it, nor faint in the hour of Temptation, which is ſuffered to come upon you for the tryal of that <hi>precious Faith,</hi> which the Lord God hath in a meaſure given unto you; but all look unto him, who is the <hi>Giver of Faith,</hi> by which the Juſt lives in Dominion over the Tempter.</p>
               <p>So let none look down at the Temptations of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil (for that will weaken, and do hurt) But all, when you are tempted, look up unto Chriſt Jeſus, the great Power and Wiſdom of God, who is given unto us by the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, to take away all Sin, and to lead into all Truth; who, in the dayes of his Fleſh (as the Apoſtle ſaid) <hi>was tempted in all points like as we are;</hi> but he did not ſin: And ſo, it is no ſin to be tempted (by the Devil) unto any wickedneſs whatſoever; but the ſin is, to conſent with the Mind unto him, and ſo to joyn to him, and ſo by him to be led to think, or ſpeak, or act that which is evil in the ſight of the Lord God; but out of all this Chriſt Jeſus doth redeem; and he is able to preſerve and uphold you in Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity and Holineſs <hi>(in all things) For he is able to ſave to the uttermoſt all, that come to the Father by him</hi> (and that is, to free from all ſin) and of this the Apoſtle was a true Witneſs, (who writ thus of him.) And though the Devil may go about you like a <hi>Roaring Lyon,</hi> ever ſeeking which of you he may devour (whom the Lord hath redeemed from him) yet, be ye not hereby Affrighted, Diſcouraged, nor caſt down in your Minds, nor deſpair of <hi>overcoming</hi> him, you tender, and contrite hearted Ones; but reſiſt him in the Faith, and be ſtedfaſt, and Chriſt will ſuccour and uphold you: So all look unto him from whom your help comes.</p>
               <p>Given forth by the Spirit of God, in the ſixth Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth, 1671. through a Try'd and True Witneſs of thoſe things, which he hath here written for the Edification
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:106804:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>and Comfort of all, who are turn'd from Darkneſs unto Light, from the power of Satan unto God: And what is here written, may be of ſome ſervice unto thoſe, who are yet Strangers from God, and his Way, and Worſhip, which is Pure.</p>
               <p>I am a Sufferer for <hi>Righteouſneſs ſake;</hi> a Priſoner (for the Teſtimony of Jeſus Chriſt, the Light and Life of men) at <hi>Maidſton</hi> in <hi>Kent,</hi> in <hi>England.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And my Heart's Deſire is, that all People might come to believe in Chriſt Jeſus, the true Light, and ſo be redeem'd by him from Sin, and ſo from the Curſe, which is due unto it, and from the Devil who is the Author of it; that ſo they might be bleſſed Eternally. And as the Holy Apoſtle ſaid, I do ſay, <hi>God would have all men to come to the Knowledge of the Truth, and be ſav'd:</hi> But Chriſt ſaid unto the Wiſe-men of the World, great Profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors; <hi>Search the Scriptures, for in them ye think ye have Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Life: but ye will not come unto me, that you might have Life.</hi> And as it was then, ſo it is now; People will not come unto Chriſt the Great Power and Wiſdom of God, to be redeem'd from Sin by him, and ſo to have Eternal Life in him; and ſo, many die in their Sins, And he ſaid, <hi>If ye believe not that I am he, you ſhall die in your Sins; and whither I go, ye cannot come.</hi> No Unclean thing can enter the Kingdom of God; and there is no Repentance in the Grave; and all who die, and periſh in their Sins, their Deſtruction is of Themſelves, and the Lord God is clear.</p>
            </div>
            <closer>
               <signed>William Gibſon.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:106804:12"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
